AKHILESH UTHAMAN

akhileshu87@gmail.com | +91-9790822300 | Bangalore, India

Professional Summary

Experienced & skilled in managing and providing engineering expertise for network engineering programs and projects through all systems development life cycle phases. Furthermore, I have in- depth knowledge of Service Provider and Enterprise business models, architectures, and solutions with an emphasis on: System Integration and design, Strategic and tactical Network Planning, Testing and troubleshooting, and Network and project Management for Telecommunications and Data networks.

Experience

Product Support Engineer III | Zscaler Pvt Ltd | 03/2024 - Current

- Gained experience in products Zscaler Internet Access (ZIA), Zscaler Private Access (ZPA) and Zscaler Digital Experience (ZDX)
- Provided phone/email consultation to independently debug complex security/network problems.
- Interface with Engineering and assist the customer with testing or troubleshooting.
- Reproduce customer issues to verify problems and provide feedback to Engineering and Operations teams.
- Create entries in our technical support on-line database to accurately document any incident resolution that is not found in our knowledge base.
- Assist in developing on-going training programs for the department.
- Promote a team environment by assisting and contributing to fellow Zscaler employees whenever necessary to
 enhance the professional development of everyone within the organization.
- Ability to mentor other engineers on advanced troubleshooting, debugging and case management skills.
- Understand the product direction and customer use-cases and provide input on product & code changes through all points of the product cycle.
- Other duties as assigned.

SECURITY CONSULTANT | IBM India Software Pvt Ltd | 01/2022 - 02/2024

- Assisted in deploying IBM Guardium collectors, aggregators and central manager servers on the Azure platform for agents like S-TAP and GIM on Oracle, SAP HANA and DB2 databases
- Assisted in integrating third-party tools like Service Now and CyberArk Vault with the Guardium tool for automation and credential security.
- Implemented & fine-tuned the policies for classification audit and security policies in Guardium for data security as well as the analytic features like outliner, and risk spotter.
- Member of the threat hunt team to perform on daily IOC & HYPO Hunt Activity.
- Microsoft KQL language & Deployed Azure Sentinel as SOAR and SIEM solutions to monitor and manage the overall security environment
- Integrated Azure Security Center, Azure AD, Firewalls, MCAS, F5 Load Balancers, & Endpoint Security solutions in Sentinel.
- Built automation of repetitive processes utilizing Sentinel workbooks, templates, and playbooks Managed Amazon Web Services like ELB, EC2, S3, RDS, CloudWatch & Assisted in implementing VPC solutions in AWS with the help of network ACLs, security groups, private and public network configurations Experience in creating and maintaining IAM policies for the organization in AWS to provide users & groups with rules based access to AWS resources, Also, hands-on experience in creating and managing S3 bucket and their policies Created Snapshots, and Amazon machine images (AMIs) of the instances for backup and clone instances Imaged part of designing/implementing the backup and archiving, disaster recovery in & Handled system routine backup, scheduling jobs, enabling system logging and reports for administration and troubleshooting.

TECHNICAL SUPPORT ENGINEER | McAfee Software | 09/2016 - 01/2022

- Handled the products McAfee Web Gateway, Unified Cloud Edge, McAfee Client Proxy and McAfee Content Security Reporter.
- Provided technical support to customers, troubleshooting software and hardware issues.
- Collaborated with cross-functional teams to resolve complex technical problems, resulting in a 30% decrease in average resolution time
- Managed customer relationships and ensured high satisfaction levels through effective communication and problem solving
- Use trace analysis (like Wireshark) and other debugging tools to analyze problems and develop solutions to meet customer needs.

SENIOR NETWORK ENGINEER | CSS CORP | 12/2015 - 09/2016

- Experienced in configuring, designing and troubleshooting security policies, NAT policies, routing, IPS and different failover mechanisms on the Palo Alto firewall
- Expert in configuring Threat prevention which includes Anti-Virus, Anti-Spyware and Vulnerability and implementing File Blocking, Wildfire analysis and DoS protection on Palo Alto Firewalls
- Expertise with configuring, Implementing and Troubleshooting remote access solutions relate to Site to Site VPN,
 Remote VPN, SSL VPN, and DMVPN.
- Extensive knowledge in implementing URL filtering, application-based policies and implementing zones.

TECHNICAL SUPPORT ENGINEER | Sandvine Pvt | 04/2015 - 07/2015

- Provided implementation assistance for the product's behaviour Policy Traffic Switch (PTS) and Subscriber Policy Broker (SPB)
- Assisted in configuring the PTS tool for functionalities like Traffic Detection, Policy Enforcement and Charging Enforcement
- Help the Communication Provider (CP) to enable the features in SPB which help to shape traffic on a persubscriber basis by applying different access policies to them (e.g., prioritize VoIP traffic to ensure sound quality for calls) Received an escalated call from Partners, technically complex mission-critical or politically hot customer issues and maintain ownership of the issue until resolved completely.

SUPPORT ENGINEER | GK HR Consultant | 03/2014 - 04/2015

- GK HR consulting (Client of McAfee)
- Worked on McAfee Email Gateway (MEG), McAfee Data Loss Prevent (DLP) and McAfee Security Microsoft Exchange (MSME) products.
- In times receive an escalated call from Partners, technically complex mission-critical or politically hot customer issues and maintain ownership of the issue until resolved completely.
- Responsible for handling the Production down the scenario of customer business and Provide information reliable resolution of the critical and highest impact problems & strategic corporate customers using the products regarding the clusters.
- Represent and communicate with corporate customers via telephone, written correspondence, or electronic service regarding technically complex and escalated problems identified in the products and manage relationships with those customers.

NETWORK ENGINEER | Top Gun Technologies | 05/2013 - 02/2014

- Installed VMware vSphere and created virtual machines on ESX Servers.
- Worked on Central Management Server (VCenter Server) to manage all the ESX hosts in the data canter.
- Worked on VMware Update Manager for updating or patching for all the ESX hosts and Virtual machines.
- Analyzing the VM-support logs for ESX servers and Virtual Center logs to diagnose the root cause for the problem.

NETWORK TRAINER | RJP Info Tek | 04/2011 - 05/2013

- Developed lesson plans, instructional materials and writing practice tests for training courses
- Organizes lab sessions and supervises students in Cisco router and switch installation, configuration, and

troubleshooting

 Organizes certification training sessions for CCNA (R&S) and CCNP (R&S) Designing, Connecting and Troubleshooting LAN/WAN environment.

Core Qualifications

- Network Security: PaloAlto (firewall), Vectra (NDR), McAfee IPS, McAfee Web Gateway, McAfee Email Gateway
- Cybersecurity: IOC based Threat Hunt, Hypo based Threat Hunt, Splunk, Microsoft Sentinel
- Cloud: AWS, Azure, Zscaler Internet Access (ZIA), Zscaler Private Access (ZPA), Zscaler Digital Experience (ZDX)
- Data Security: IBM Guardium (DAM), McAfee Data Loss Prevention (DLP)
- Endpoint Security: Microsoft Defender (XDR)
- Protocol: SMTP, SAML, LDAP, KERBEROS, DNS, DHCP, FTP, OSPF, BGP, STP, VLAN, NAT (S-NAT, U-NAT and D-NAT), VPN (IPsec and GRE), SSL, TCP, HTTP, ICAP

Education

Amrita Vishwa Vidyapeetham College, Amrita University | Kerala India | 2010

Bachelor of Computer Science: Computer

GPA: 5.9

Sri Vidhya Mandir High School | Kerala India

Certificate of Higher Education

Languages

English, Hindi, Malayalam

Certifications

CCNP (R&S)

CCNA (Security)

PCNSA

AWS (SAA-C01)

MICROSOFT (SC-200), (AZ 104)

Zscaler Certified Cloud Professional (ZCCP)